<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true discourse of all the royal passages, tryumphs and ceremonies, obserued at the contract and mariage of the high and mighty Charles, King of Great Britaine, and the most excellentest of ladies, the Lady Henrietta Maria of Burbon, sister to the most Christian King of France Together with her iourney from Paris to Bulloigne, and thence vnto Douer in England, where the King met her, and the manner of their enterview. As also the tryumphant solemnities which passed in their iournies from Douer to the citie of London, and so to Whitehall, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18475</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5030</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111856</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847117</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847117</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12129</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18475)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12129)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1342:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true discourse of all the royal passages, tryumphs and ceremonies, obserued at the contract and mariage of the high and mighty Charles, King of Great Britaine, and the most excellentest of ladies, the Lady Henrietta Maria of Burbon, sister to the most Christian King of France Together with her iourney from Paris to Bulloigne, and thence vnto Douer in England, where the King met her, and the manner of their enterview. As also the tryumphant solemnities which passed in their iournies from Douer to the citie of London, and so to Whitehall, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, [16], 29-36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Hauiland for Hanna Barret,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Quires d-e, unpaginated, contain interpolated speeches. Variant (early state?): lacking these quires.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Henrietta Maria, --  Queen, consort of Charles I, King of England, 1609-1669 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12129:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12129:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E</hi> DISCOVRSE OF ALL THE ROYAL PASSAGES, TRYVMPHS and Ceremonies, obſerued at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and Mariage of the High and Mighty CHARLES, <hi>King of Great</hi> Britaine, <hi>and the</hi> moſt Excellenteſt of Ladies, the Lady HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIETTA MARIA of <hi>Burbon,</hi> ſiſter to <hi>the moſt Chriſtian King of</hi> FRANCE.</p>
            <p>Together with her Iourney from <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> and thence vnto <hi>Douer</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> where the KING met her, and the manner of their enterview.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo the tryumphant Solemnities which</hi> paſſed in their Iournies from <hi>Douer</hi> to the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> and ſo to Whitehall, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <l>O quam te memorem virgo. —</l>
               <l>— O Dea Certe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by IOHN HAVILAND for HANNA BARRET. 1625.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="relation">
            <pb facs="tcp:12129:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12129:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> TRVE RELATION of all the Royall Paſſages, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes and Ceremonies, obſerued at the Contract and Mariage of the High and mightie CHARLES, King of Great <hi>Britaine,</hi> and the moſt Excellenteſt of Ladies, the Lady HENRIETTA MARIA of <hi>Burbon,</hi> Siſter to the moſt <hi>Chriſtian King of France,</hi> together with Her Iourney from <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> and thence vnto <hi>Douer</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and ſo to the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt all the infinite bleſſings wherewith it hath pleaſed the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Goodneſſe to cloath and adorne our Nation: None is more remarkeable or glorious, then this happie and long wiſht
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12129:3"/> for Vnion betweene the two great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies of <hi>France</hi> and Great <hi>Britaine,</hi> ſince by it wee haue attained to the full height of all our hopes, all our wiſhes, all our contentments, and beholding, as in a goodly Myrrour, the full pourtrature of all our ioyes, we finde our Kingdome fortified againſt the threatnings of Enuie, our throne eſtabliſhed with the hope of a moſt flouriſhing Iſſue, and the hearts of all true ſubiects reuiued with the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of this bleſſed Match, and Coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: which may worke terror amongſt our aduerſaries, as oft as they heare the ioynt names of Great <hi>Britaine</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> in a chearefull manner repeated.</p>
            <p>To proceed then to thoſe Royall Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages and triumphant Ceremonies which were performed at theſe great Nuptials. It is to be vnderſtood that vpon Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, being the eight of May, according to the <hi>French</hi> Computation, but the eight and twentieth of Aprill, according to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> account, the moſt <hi>Christian King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> with his Queene, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12129:3"/> the Prince his onely Brother, and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by my Lords the Dukes of <hi>Nemeurs</hi> and <hi>Elbeuf,</hi> the two great Marſhalls of <hi>France, Mounſieur de Vitry</hi> and <hi>Baſſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piere,</hi> With a world of other Noble-men, Ladies, Knights and Gentlemen, came forth of his Bed-chamber or Cabinet, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the publique Preſence Chamber, where he ſent for the moſt Excellent Lady his Siſter, who with all Solemnitie was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently brought forth by the Queene her Mother, and attended on by the Princeſſe of <hi>Conde,</hi> the Princeſſe of <hi>Countee,</hi> the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Cheureuſe,</hi> and the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Elbeuf,</hi> and diuers other Ladies of State, and Maides of Honour: Her garments that day were exceeding rich and ſumptuous, her Gowne being of cloth of gold, cut vpon cloth of ſiluer, and richly embrode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all ouer with <hi>Flower de Luces</hi> of gold, and chaſed and interlaid with Dimonds, Rubies, Pearle, and other rich Iuelrie of an ineſtimable valew: Her Traine was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12129:4"/> borne vp by the young Lady of <hi>Burbon,</hi> her deare Kinſwoman, and a Ladie of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great beautie and wonderfull ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration.</p>
            <p>After the Princeſſe had in reuerend and ſolemne wiſe done obeyſance to the King her Brother, in which action of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie a man might haue beheld all the glorious beames of Maieſtie and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: there preſently entred into the Chamber the Earle of <hi>Carlile,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Holland,</hi> being both Ambaſſadors for his Maieſtie of Great <hi>Britaine;</hi> and both ſo rich and ſumptuouſly attired, that neither art nor wealth was able to exceed them. Theſe two noble men in a moſt ſolemne and reſpectiue manner Deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the King of <hi>France</hi> the Contract of Mariage, which was forthwith opened and publikely read by the Secretary of the Kings Cabinet in an high and audible voice, and then all other Couenants and agreements concluded vpon, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract was allowed and ratified by the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12129:4"/> Lord Chancellour, who made a congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulatory ſpeech in honour of that daies Ceremonie.</p>
            <p>Aſſoone as theſe things were perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ambaſſadors with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew themſelues into the Duke of <hi>Cheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuſe</hi> Chamber which was the Kings lodgings, when all accommodations ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for them and that daies ſolemnitie was in goodly order prepared, here the Embaſſadours communicated vnto the Duke the Contract, who forthwith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned againe to the King his Maſter, hauing the Embaſſadours alſo with him, and diuers other Noblemen of great ranke and place. The Duke was alſo himſelfe moſt richly attired, and though the ground was blacke, yet was the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brodery of admirable value, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Diamonds and other Precious ſtones beſtowed within the ſame, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially vpon the panes of his breeches and the tagges of his points, which were praiſed at an infinite world of treaſure.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:12129:5"/>
            <p>Aſſoone as the Duke was come before the King (after ſolemne reuerence done) hee preſented to his Highneſſe his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curation, and ſhewed the authoritie and Commiſſion which the King of great <hi>Britaine</hi> had giuen him, being in a certaine ſcedule annexed and fixt vnto the Contract, which after the King had read, hee allowed and ſigned alſo: ſo did the great Lady her ſelfe the Queene of <hi>France,</hi> and the Queene Mother, the Duke of <hi>Cheuruſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> to whom the proxey belonged, and both the Embaſſadours for <hi>England;</hi> then all things being brought to this perfection, the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>de la Roche Faucault</hi> attyred in all his pontificall roabes, after the cuſtome and manner of the <hi>French</hi> Nation perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Contract and publiſhed the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance in a moſt ſtately and reuerend manner, to the infinite ioy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of all the beholders, and the vnſpeakeable comfort and proſperity of both the happy Kingdomes.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:12129:5"/>
            <p>This Contract thus happily perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Kings Pallace of the <hi>Louure,</hi> forthwith our Ladies Church in <hi>Paris</hi> is choſen for the Celebration and finall concluſion of the euer-happy mariage; and that it might bee the fitter for the receipt of ſo great a pompe and ſtate, it was out of hand hang'd all ouer with wonderfull rich Arras, cloth of Tiſſue, cloth of Gold, and cloth of Siluer; there was alſo in the ſame Church raiſed vp vpon goodly pillaſters and gilt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbs a moſt rich and ſtately gallery or Scaffold of ſtate, which extended from the firſt entry of the Archbiſhops houſe to the very Quire or vppermoſt end of the ſame Church, being a ſtructure of ſuch good liues, that art could not poſſible expreſſe any thing beyond it. The Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars and railes which did vnderprop this gallery were at the top couered with a very curious Purple or Violet coloured Sattin, all imbrodered and powdred ouer with golden Flower de Luces, and at the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12129:6"/> bottomes they were ouerſpread with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fine white linnen and many burning tapers of waxe flaming about the ſame, ſo that the Church ſeemed like the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of the Sunne, deſcribed by <hi>Ouid</hi> in his ſecond Booke of the tranſmutations of ſhapes.</p>
            <p>Through this Gallery the whole pompe and body of this Royall and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matchable ſolemnity was to paſſe, which I haue thought good briefely to ſet downe as I receiued it from thoſe which were Noble eye witneſſes of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the perfixed day and houre for the ſolemnitie of this Royall and ſacred Mariage being come, and the whole pompe thereof in a full readineſſe, the firſt that marched forth were the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Swiſſers of the Kings Guard all cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in the Kings liuery of eſtate with their Drummes beating before and after them, the Fifes whiſtling, their Enſigne diſplayed, and all other things ſutable to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12129:6"/> a warlike preparation, for theſe are the Kings firſt, and indeede moſt ſouldier-like guard, being men of that temper and condition, that they are truely ſaid to be borne Souldiers, liue Souldiers, and dye Souldiers. A good pretty ſpace af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them went twelue Hoboyes in the Kings liuery of Eſtate alſo, who playing vpon thoſe loud Inſtruments ſtrucke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome admiration, but into all delight and pleaſure. Next vnto theſe marcht in two ranckes eight of the Kings principall Drummes in their Liueries of Eſtate alſo, and theſe were ſaid to beat their Drums with that brauery and couragiouſneſſe, that as it was ſaid of <hi>Alexander,</hi> that when he heard Ionicke muſicke, he would ſtart vp, call for his ſword and armour, and expreſſe all the paſſions of anger and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſo there was not an eare that heard theſe, but awaked the heart to thinke of heroycall atchieuements. After theſe marched the Kings ſecond Guard, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of Frenchmen: Then came at leaſt a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12129:7"/> dozen Trumpets in their Liueries of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate alſo, with rich Banners containing the Kings full Coat Armour, and faire Cordans of watchet ſilke and gold ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the reſt in euery proportion. After theſe Trumpets came in a ſtately manner <hi>Mounſieur de Rhodes,</hi> who is the great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Ceremonies, being wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly richly apparrelled, and at the leaſt twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Kings ordinary Gentlemen at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending about him. Immediately after him went all the Lords, and others who were Knights of the great and renowned Order of the Holy Ghoſt, in the rich Roabs of their Order, and with their Palkes or Mantles of watchet veluet all, moſt brauely embrodered with <hi>Flower de Luces</hi> of gold, and their other garments ſhining with pretious ſtones and rich Iuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Neare vnto theſe Knights went ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Heralds at Armes in very rich Coats of Crimſon Veluet, with the Armes of <hi>France,</hi> and all powdred ouer with gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>Flower de Luces.</hi> Cloſe vnto theſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12129:7"/> Heraulds followed the two great great Marſhalls of <hi>France, Mounſieur de Vitry,</hi> and <hi>Mounſieur Baſſompiere;</hi> and after them came alone the Duke of <hi>Elbeuf</hi> in moſt ſumptuous attire. Then a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from him came (repreſenting the Perſon of the Royall Bride-groome) the Duke of <hi>Cheureuſe,</hi> in a ſute of moſt rich perfumed blackecloth, cut vpon cloth of gold, and lined with rich Tiſſue; vpon his head he wore a Cap of cloth of gold, on which was fixed a Iewell of a moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable value, euery Diamond being ſo glorious, that it dazelled the eyes of all that gazed vpon it; about his body Bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricke-wiſe he wore a wonderfull curious rich Scarffe, all embrodered ouer with Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and powdred with Paragon Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, and great orient Pearle; he wore a ſhort cloake all embrodered ouer with gold, and ſet with Diamonds ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thicke and furiouſly, that in his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing hee ſeemed to burne and beare a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing flame about him. After him came
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12129:8"/> the Earle of <hi>Carlile,</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (being the Extraordinary Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors for the Maieſtie of Great <hi>Britaine</hi>) and they were both apparrelled in white cloth of ſiluer, richly embrodered and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchaſed with many pretious ſtones and wealthie Iuelry. Then came the King of <hi>France</hi> in his owne Perſon, in Royall garments of Eſtate, all embrodered ouer with gold and ſiluer, and almoſt couered ouer with rich Iewels, in his right hand holding the moſt Excellent Princeſſe his ſiſter, who that day wore a Crowne of gold vpon her head, chaſed and ſet with Diamonds, and a world of other pretious ſtones, her Gowne was all powdred ouer with golden <hi>Flower de Luces:</hi> and on her other hand went <hi>Mounſieur</hi> the Kings Brother, wonderfull ſumptuouſly attired, and not inferiour to any that hac place in the Royall aſſembly. Next vnto the King, Prince, and Royall Bride, followed the Queen Mother of <hi>France,</hi> very graue, yet richly attired: and after her came the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12129:8"/> Queene of <hi>France,</hi> whoſe Gowne was all lulyeoly, embrodered ouer with gold and ſiluer, and ſet, and inchaſed with a world of pretious ſtones, Pearle, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iuelry; the Princeſſe of <hi>Conde,</hi> and the Princeſſe of <hi>Countee</hi> bore vp the Queenes long Traine. And after them followed the young Ladie of <hi>Montpenſier,</hi> and the Counteſſe of <hi>Soyſons,</hi> and other Ladies of the Kings bloud, in rich gownes brodered about with golden <hi>Flower de Luces.</hi> And after them the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Cheureuſe,</hi> and the Dutcheſſe <hi>Elbeuf,</hi> with a world of other Ladies and Gentlewomen, which like ſo many faire Planets mouing in their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall orbes, made all the place like the Heauens ſparkle with renowne and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry about them. After theſe came a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle world of Noble-men, Knights, and Gentlemen. And laſt of all came the Kings principall and chiefe Guard, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting onely of <hi>Stots</hi> and no other.</p>
            <p>All this royall and admired aſſemblie
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12129:9"/> hauing in this worthie equipage before deſcribed, aduanced themſelues from the Kings Caſtle of the Louure to our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Church, they all made a ſtand at the entrie of the great porch of the Church, before which was a moſt ſtately ſcaffold mounted whereon to celebrate the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and in which place was raiſed a wonderfull rich and curious Canopie or vealt royall of cloth of gold richly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brodred, and held almoſt of and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable valew: to this Canopie or Vealt royall the King and Monſieur his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conducted the Royall Bride their ſiſter, and placing her vnder it, they there left her till ſome ceremonie were fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, then they reſigned her vp into the hands of the Duke of Chereuſe, to whom the Cardinall <hi>de la Roche Foncault</hi> came and performed all the ceremonies of marriage according to the orders of the Church, and the royall ceremonies of the French Nation, all acclamations of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and renowne ringing about the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12129:9"/> Church in a wonderfull manner.</p>
            <p>The ceremonies being thus finiſhed all, the troopes and orders before rehearſed, paſſed in a moſt ſolemne manner vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the quire through along the gallerie, principally erected for that purpoſe, and going by a direct line, iuſt through the middeſt of the Church, and euery part thereof hung and adorned with won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull rich cloth of Arras, being more then three quarters of gold or ſiluer.</p>
            <p>In the middeſt of the quire on both ſides were placed diuers eminent and ſtately ſeates of more reſpect and view then any formerly repeated, on the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ſide whereof ſate all my Lords the Preſidents of the Parliaments of France, with their morters of gold vpon their heads, and their gownes, robes and hoods of rich ſcarlet all lined with Ermines, and ſome ſmall degree below them ſat all the Councellors of the high Courts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in gownes like vnto the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and other things appropriated vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their places.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:12129:10"/>
            <p>In oppoſition vnto theſe, and in ſeats of like eminence, ſat firſt alone by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the Prouoſt of the Merchants of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, cloathed in a long roabe of Crimſon and Purple, or Violet coloured Veluet, and neere vnto him the Sherifes of the Citie of Paris, and other principall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates which were of eſpeciall note both in the Citie and in the Vniuerſitie.</p>
            <p>Not far from theſe ſeates, and in the quire alſo was mounted another ſcaffold or flore, being raiſed full three ſteps high, vpon which was mounted another large and goodly Canopie or Tent royall, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which the K. the Q. and the Q. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Kings brother were placed and conducted this thereby the Duke of Cheureuſe, and the two extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie Embaſſadors for the maieſtie of great Brittaine, who after they had ſeene euerie ceremonie fitted, they withdrew themſelues into the Archbiſhops pallace vntil the whole ſeruice was ended, &amp; then they returned againe to the K. &amp; Queene.</p>
            <p>When the formes or ceremonies of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12129:10"/> French deuotions were ended, and that the acclamations of the people had cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ioy to euery proceeding, then the whole troope returned, in the ſame forme or equipage as they came thither vnto the Archbiſhops pallace, where the whole Court ſupped, and were entertained with all the ſtate, pompe, and magnificence that could bee deuiſed. During all the pompe and ſolemnitie of which feaſt, there was heard ſuch thundring vollies of Cannon, and other great ſhot that the ecchoing report thereof was carried ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny leagues off, and euen iudgement it ſelfe could not but ſtand amazed to ſee and heare the wonderfull terrors which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from pleaſure and reioycings. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe infinite vollies of ſhot, was ſeene many other triumphes, as bonefires, fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes, feaſts, muſickes of all kinds, and all ſounds, dancings, maskings, &amp; all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of reuells, that France ſeemed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend nothing but the preſent rauiſhing ioy, &amp; well; &amp; truly may it be ſaid of her
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12129:11"/> that then now ſhe was neuer ſeene more pleaſant, neuer more abundantly clothed with contentments and comforts.</p>
            <p>But here leaſt I might be thought to gallop too ſwiftly ouer the glorie of this high ſtate and magnificence, and like the dogs vpon the riuer Nilus to catch here and there a lap running, I will borrow leaue a little to ſpeake of the powerfull ſtate and magnificence of this hardly pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralleld feaſt and ſumptuous triumph.</p>
            <p>It is therefore firſt to be vnderſtood that this glorious and royall feaſt was held in the great hall belonging to the Archbiſhops pallace, being a roome of wonderfull long extent, the table ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out from the one end of the hall to the other, and being couered and adorned with wonderfull rich damaske, and the ſalts and other apparrell of infinite price and valew, the King of France ſat in the middeſt of the table, and was ſerued by the grand Prior of France, who that day repreſented the perſon of the great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12129:11"/> of France, before him marched eight drums, foure fifes, and ſixteene trumpets, beſides a world of clarions, hoboyes, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and other loud inſtruments, his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was accompanied with <hi>Monſieur Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aumont,</hi> Lord grand Steward of the kings houſe, and two and thirtie other inferior Stewards of his Maieſties houſhold with white ſtaues in their hands, and other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of their ſeuerall places.</p>
            <p>The meat was this day carried vp by the Lords, Princes, Dukes, Peeres, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals, and Barons of France, followed by Knights, Eſquires, Gentlemen of the Court, and other inferiour officers and ſeruants. Now touching the particular ſeruices of ſtate, you ſhall vnderſtand that <hi>Monſier Iainuilde</hi> ſerued this day as the Lord great Pantler of France, the Duke of Elbeufe was Cupbearer, and the Earle of Harcourt was Caruer. The Queene mother ſat on the right hand of the King, and her perſon was attended by the Duke of Belgard principall Sewer,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12129:12"/> the Duke of Vzias, and the Duke of Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embourge. The Queene of France her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſat on the right hand of the Queene mother, and was attended by the Duke of Aluine, the Duke <hi>Briſſac,</hi> and the Duke of Chaune. The Queene of great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſat on the Kings left hand, and was attended by the Marſhall <hi>de Vittry,</hi> who ſerued her as great Pantler, the Marſhall <hi>de Aubeterce,</hi> who ſerued her as Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer, and the Marſhall <hi>Baſſampiere</hi> as Caruer. My Lord the Duke of Cheureuſe ſat next the Queene of great Brittaine, and was attended by the Lord of Roch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. The Earle of Carlile, and the Earle of Holland Embaſſadors for the Maieſty of great Brittaine ſate next the Duke of Cheureuſe, and laſtly <hi>Monſier</hi> the Kings brother ſate neere vnto the Queene, and after him the reſt of the Peeres and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, all which were ſerued and attended on in moſt magnificent and heroycall manner.</p>
            <p>After the ſolemnitie of this great
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12129:12"/> and royall feaſt, the King, Queenes, and Princes returned backe to the Louuer, where there was great ſtore of Muſicke, Dauncing, and Reuells, and the ioy of that daies happie and bleſſed vnion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued the night of her ordinarie accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed dues, ſo that reſt was in a manner quite forgotten, and the night and day were both thought too ſcant and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to expreſſe a ioy ſo ſtrong and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated.</p>
            <p>After theſe ceremonies and celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were to the contentment of all true hearted ſubiects finiſhed, the euer admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and moſt excellent Queene of great Brittaine, after ſome ſhort time of repoſe, with a wonderfull glorious traine of Princes, Noblemen, Ladies, and all the choiceſt flowres of France, tooke her hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie iourney towards Bulloyne, where af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome trauell, and the expence of ſome few daies, her Maieſtie arriued with great proſperitie; for in that place lay at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor the goodly fleet of great Brittaine,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12129:13"/> readie to waft and carrie her Maieſtie ouer at her owne appointment, and in the paſſage of this fleet, there was one thing remarkeable, as that in their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from England the wind roſe vp ſo full South and South-Weſt, being the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wind which was oppoſite and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to their courſe, that but with infinite great trouble and vexation they had power to attaine to the French ſhore, but being there arriued, immediatly the wind roſe vp full North-Eaſt, which was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the moſt contrarie wind for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne that could poſſibly blow from any part of the Compaſſe, neither was the Contrariety of this winde of a meane and indifferent nature, but ſo violent, feirce and impatient that it was hardly poſſible for any Ship to liue or Continue vpon that roade, and although the neceſſity of their preſent occaſion, the command and ſeruice to which was bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the vttermoſt of there obedience, and many other tyes inforſt them to vſe all Art, Care and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12129:13"/> ſtill to continue in that place, yet was the impatience of the winds ſo great that in deſpight of all art or induſtry the goodly and tall ſhip called the <hi>Prince</hi> ſpent an anchor of aboue 30. hundred weight, the <hi>Anne,</hi> the <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> and all the reſt of the fleete were on drift, and all hope be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cut off to continue longer in that place, and they muſt now looke for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne ſafetie. But <hi>Ecce quam opportunum,</hi> behold how great and good our God is in theſe fatall extremities, for in the very minute of this Deſperation and Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment the <hi>Queene</hi> of great <hi>Britaine</hi> came to <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> and as if her very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence had diſpeld the winde, or the ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of her excellent nature, had put into inſenſible things a ſenſible feeling of the Iniuries which might be done to her goodnes by the impatiencie of ſuch ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my weather, preſently the ſtorme &amp; winds ceaſed and the Sea became ſo calme and milde that not a wrinkle was to be ſeene vpon <hi>Neptunes</hi> face, &amp; the windes as if
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12129:14"/> they ſtrugled to Conduct &amp; bring her to the place where both her royal Lords and her own wiſhes and the peoples longings hourely aſpired and that withall eaſe comfort and ſweeteneſſe, they preſently roſe vp ſo calmely and with ſuch deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate breath that Ioyning with the gentleneſſe of the eaſie tides all ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily concurred together that not the beſt wiſh was able to out-reach the happy euent.</p>
            <p>This obſeruation being taken both by her Excellent ſelfe, and thoſe carefull Princes who had the charge of her Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Perſon, ſhee preſently tooke her Barge vpon Sunday about ten of the clocke in the fore-noone, being the ninth of this inſtant Iune, according to our Engliſh computation and ſo came a boord a goodly and ſtately ſhip, called the Prince, being Admirall, where after a world of ſhouts, prayers, vowes and acclamations for the proſperitie of her happie iourney; they hoiſted ſaile, and came that day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb facs="tcp:12129:14"/> ſix of the clocke in the after-noone vnto the Towne of <hi>Douer</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> where ſhe was receiued with that ioy and humble reſpect, that neuer Queene could boaſt of a more generall applauſe. From the water ſhee was conducted in moſt ſtately and magnificent manner to <hi>Douer</hi> Caſtle, where her Highneſſe repoſed her ſelfe that night, being royally entertained both by the Towne and Countrey, and magnificently feaſted and accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with all the delights and pleaſures which the leaſure of that buſie affaire could giue any libertie vnto.</p>
            <p>Vpon Munday being the thirteenth of Iune, the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie came vnto <hi>Douer</hi> about ten of the clocke in the fore-noone, and after little ſhort preparation, the Queene being full of all ioyfull expectation, they met together in the Priuie Chamber, where in the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter ſhe threw her ſelfe into his armes with that boundleſſe and vnexpreſſeable affection, that vertue, modeſtie, and all the
<pb facs="tcp:12129:15"/> perfections which can crowne the beſt and moſt excellent creature, might there haue learned the worthieſt rules both of honour, true loue, and obedience; neither did ſhee ſo ſoone caſt her ſelfe into his armes, as withall inſtantly threw downe her ſelfe vpon her knees before him, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vp into his ſacred protection, her life, libertie, ſeruice, and euerlaſting obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, acknowledging her ſelfean Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid to his goodneſſe, and that all the powers and ſtrength both of her minde and bodie ſhould wholly and abſolutely, next vnto her God, reſt euer bound to his Kingly Commandements. What tongue or pen is able to expreſſe that ioy where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he receiued her, and her deare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, for ſcarſely could you ſay ſhee is now vpon her knees, when with all the tenderneſſes which an immaculate and vnſpotted affection could expreſſe, hee preſently tooke her vp into his armes, kiſt her againe, and gaue her thoſe deare expreſſions of a neuer changing loue,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12129:15"/> that the beholders might ſee how each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers heart flew out at the windowes of their eyes, and by adeliazan enterchange lodged themſelues in each others bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome: after theſe pure and vnfained careſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they fell into priuate conference, and ſo paſſed the time till dinner; which finiſhed, the King and Queene depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Douer,</hi> and being come out of the Towne, a gallant volley of ſhot was deliuered both from the Caſtle and ſhips, which continued ſo long and loud, that the very peale in the eccho carried backe her royall welcome vnto <hi>Callyes.</hi> Being come from the Towne of <hi>Douer,</hi> they came vpon <hi>Barrome</hi> Downe, a ſpatious and goodly place, where were aſſembled all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobilitie, and many La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Honour and high place, which being ranckt according to the dignitie of their great places, and the knight Marſhall with a carefull reſpect keeping the vulgar from intruding or doing them offence. The King and Queene in great State rode
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12129:16"/> betweene them, giuing ſuch reſpect and grace to euery one of deſeruing quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that euery one ſtroue in their prayers and praiſes, to let the world vnderſtand the infiniteneſſe of their ioy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Barrome</hi> Downe the King and Queene came the ſame night to the Citie of <hi>Canterburie,</hi> all the wayes whereupon they rode being ſtrewed with greene ruſhes, Roſes, and the choiſeſt flowers that could be gotten, and the trees loaden with people of all ſorts, who with ſhouts and acclamations gaue them a continuall welcome. Being come neare vnto the Citie, their Highneſſes were met, and receiued by the Maior, and the reſt of the Citie Magiſtrates, and ſo brought within the walles, where was pronounced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them diuers learned gratulatory Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſuch infinite preparations made of all kindes for the generall entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that <hi>Canterbury</hi> ſeemed for that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time, a very <hi>Eden</hi> or <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> where
<pb facs="tcp:12129:16"/> nothing was wanting that might ſerue ioy or delight.</p>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>Maſter IOHN FINCH his Speech to King CHARLES at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> May 30. 1625.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MOſt Gratious and dread Soueraigne:</hi> Thoſe that would keepe their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in a iuſt and true temper, vſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for ſpeech or action, had need of a watchfull eye vpon two principall cauſes of their decay, the ouer-contracting, and the too-much extending of them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the laſt doth moſt impoueriſh and weaken: whence it commeth, that in weightie griefes the ſpirits being pent vp and impriſoned, haue often the doores of vtterance ſhut againſt them: but in exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue ioy, where they ſpread and make haſt to get forth by expreſſion, they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſcattered and loſt.</p>
               <p>Both theſe are at this time combined
<pb facs="tcp:12129:17"/> againſt vs, your Maieſties humbleſt and meaneſt ſubiects.</p>
               <p>When we remember what a glorious and good King wee haue loſt. A King from his cradle to thoſe very yeeres that are the common meaſure of this ſhort line of Life, exerciſed in all the wiſdome of well gouerning. A King that hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away the wall of Separation united two puiſſant and military Nations redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Ireland</hi> by forren plantations, gaue this Realme a large portion of the new world, and reigned aboue twentie yeares in ſuch peace and felicitie, as was beyond the euent of former times; for euen in the happie daies of Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous memory, her firſt yeares were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted by a Rebellion in <hi>England,</hi> and her laſt by a Rebellion in <hi>Ireland.</hi> A King that by his incomparable Writings, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed himſelfe true <hi>Defender of the Faith;</hi> and like <hi>Ioſua,</hi> made the walles of ſpirituall <hi>Ierico</hi> fall downe before him. When wee but remember this (as who
<pb facs="tcp:12129:17"/> can euer forget it) how are our ſorrowes preſt together, or who can finde any doore of ſpeech to let his griefe forth at? <hi>Non eſt dolor ſicut iste,</hi> There is no wo can parallel this.</p>
               <p>But when we turne our eies and hearts vpon your moſt excellent Maieſtie, the true Heire of all his Princely Vertues, when in your Royall Perſon wee ſee all theſe bleſſings and fauours of God entai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon vs, and by this happie Coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction now deſcendable to all poſteritie: who can draw forth the Legions of his ioy in order, or finde a language fit for the gladneſſe of his heart.</p>
               <p>He that is borne a King <hi>(moſt Gratious Soueraigne)</hi> can hardly attaine one point of perfection in Gouernment, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of obeying well. A contemplation which in one act of obedience in <hi>Henry</hi> the fift, (who was one of the nobleſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that euer ſwayed the Scepter of this Kingdome from the Conqueſt to his times, and he matched with a Daughter of <hi>France</hi>) gaue extraordinary comfort
<pb facs="tcp:12129:18"/> vnto his Father, a wiſe and prudent King. What happineſſe then hath your Maieſtie ſealed vs an aſſurance of, who hauing in all the actions of your life beene an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Sonne to your Royall Father, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be other then an excellent Father to your people. On the Throne <hi>(for Hills beſt diſcouer Valleyes)</hi> Princes may with much aduantage, as in a perſpectiue glaſſe draw the ſtate of the Common-wealth nearer their ſight; but when they deſcend from themſelues, and grow acquainted with the hearts and affections of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects; this is to meaſure the Valleyes at hand, and not at diſtance, and doth at once winne hope of their goodneſſe, and make vs in awe of their wiſdome.</p>
               <p>Such were the effects of your Maieſties Princely Iudgement, when in the laſt (by you made happie) Parlament, and in the Aſſembly preceding it, your Highneſſe, <hi>Exuta purpura,</hi> forgetting you were the only Sonne of the King, became the Son of the Kingdome, and tooke vpon your ſelfe the cares and deſires of it. (By which,
<pb facs="tcp:12129:18"/> as by the balme of Gilead, our wounds were healed in time, and all of vs as much incouraged (in humble and dutifull manner) to preſent our iuſt greuances vnto you, as we are deterred from crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any ſuch out of our owne vaine or vnmannerly fancies. Your Maieſties beames like thoſe of the Sunne-riſing were then moſt comfortable, now that your Maieſtie is in the exaltation of your orbe, we cannot but hope to finde more benigne and ſerene aſpects.</p>
               <p>But there is yet one ioy aboue all theſe and which ſeaſons all our other bleſſings, your Maieſties ſo knowne and knowing zeale for true religion. Princes indued with morall vertues are like Diamonds, rich, but rough and vnpoliſhed, it is the knowledge and feare of God only adds the true luſter and ſets them faire.</p>
               <p>This was our vnſpeakable comfort, and a bleſſing <hi>England</hi> muſt neuer be vnmindfull of, when you our Sunne were in the Weſt, and a full halfe yeares night clouded all our hearts with a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full darkeneſſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12129:19"/>
               <p>Let it not (moſt gratious and mighty King) be regiſtred in your Royall heart amongſt the errors of this City, that your Highneſſe was heere ſtayed in that your Iourney, (for I ſee they are damp at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of it) and humbly expect to haue their pardon ſealed by one gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious looke of yours.</p>
               <p>True it is, like vnskilled Aſtronomers, not knowing the Sunnes proper courſe, we had all our eyes only on the rapid motion of thoſe times. But therein theſe your Maieſties faithfull ſubiects did but in little draw a perfect modell of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret votes and deſires of your whole Kingdome, which afterwards vpon your Highneſſe returne, brake forth into flames of ioy not vnacceptable vnto you.</p>
               <p>The hearty affection of your ſubiects is like the ſoule of man, all in all, and all in euery part of your Kingdome. Vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe then (moſt Gratious and Soueraigne Leige) as in that, ſo now from theſe your humble and faithfull ſubiects, the Maior, Aldermen, and whole commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty
<pb facs="tcp:12129:19"/> of this City, graciouſly to accept that Loyall and hearty welcome which the fulneſſe of ioy makes dew from all, and be not diſpleaſed, if as <hi>Iacob</hi> did the King of Kings, we haue once more ſtayed your Maieſtie till wee might receiue a bleſſing from you.</p>
               <p>This City (my moſt gratious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne) hath beene the ſeate of Kings and in repute amongſt other Cities of this Kingdome. <hi>Velut inter ignes Luna mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</hi> In King <hi>Ethelberts</hi> time aboue a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares ſince, it was <hi>Caput imperij ſui:</hi> and by his donation to <hi>Auſten</hi> made the firſt Archbiſhops Sea, in which the moſt part of threeſcore and foureteene Metri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politans haue kept their reſidence.</p>
               <p>Many of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings lie buried heere, and ſince the conqueſt <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, the firſt King of the line of <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter,</hi> and that famous <hi>Edward</hi> the black Prince, who brought almoſt as much ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to <hi>France</hi> as your Maieſtie hath now done ioy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fuimus Troes,</hi> but by fier and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb facs="tcp:12129:20"/> worſe then that (Inteſtiue diſcord and diſſention) it hath beene ſo often torne and defaced, that ſcarce any foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of the ancient ſplendor are now to be diſcouered. Some fauours only of your Maieſties Royall Progenitors haue kept life in it, and held it vp by the Chinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the third endowed it with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ample priuiledges.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt beſtowed the Maioral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vpon vs, from whoſe time downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>Dum nos aliquod nomenque decuſque Geſsimus,</hi> forty together of the beſt name and bloud in this country, beare that office heere.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth made it a County of it ſelfe, ſeuered and diſtinct from the reſt of <hi>Kent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your Maieſties moſt Royall Father (of euer bleſſed and happy memory) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed all our ancient liberties and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on vs this ſword, the enſigne of Honor and Iuſtice.</p>
               <p>The competent diſtance from the Sea,
<pb facs="tcp:12129:20"/> and a Riuer that with no great coſt might be made nauigable, ſhew how na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall apt it is to embrace great traffique: And ſince it is the ſtayers by which all Ambaſſadors of forraigne Princes and ſtrangers aſcend your Imperiall chamber of <hi>London,</hi> we hope it will one day bee held not vnworthy the high thoughts of ſo great and glorious a King as King <hi>Charles,</hi> to make it in ſome ſort proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable to the reſt of that building.</p>
               <p>It had once a Mint in it, but this poore preſent, will quickly tell your Maieſtie that is gone. Only as the glory of ſtarrs is not alwayes in their magnitude, wee hope the humble Zeale with which it is offered will finde your Maieſties Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and benigne Interpretation.</p>
               <p>The God of <hi>Dauid</hi> be euer with King <hi>Charles,</hi> and make his throne greater then the throne of his Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <pb facs="tcp:12129:21"/>
               <head>Maſter IOHN FINCH his Speech to King CHARLES and <hi>his Queene at Canterbury, Iune.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1625.</head>
               <p>IN all Sacrifices vnder the Law, <hi>Moſt High and Mightie King (Moſt Gratious and moſt Illuſtrious Queen)</hi> two things were of Principall vſe and myſterie, <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Salt,</hi> one taught vs the neceſſitie of Zeale, the other how to make that Zeale acceptable by right guiding &amp; ordering of it: for prepoſterous Zeale is like an excellent Inſtrument well ſtrung, but out of tune. The glory and grace now ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vpon vs from your High Maieſties, like the heauenly fire of <hi>Elias Sacrifice,</hi> hath ſo filled our ſoules with ioy and gladneſſe, that our humble and heartie expreſſions can neuer diſtruſt your grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous acceptations, when all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to inflame the zeale of Engliſh harts, that we could hope, or our Enemies feare.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12129:21"/>
               <p>This happie Vnion of two great and Potent Kingdoms in this ſo glorious and bleſſed Coniunction of your moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maieſties, and this <hi>Regina votorum,</hi> this faire Daughter of <hi>France,</hi> whom our prayers and earneſt expectations haue ſo long attended. Kingdomes are but E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitomies of the World, as families are of them, yet in good neighbours both take comfort. If we credit ſome remaines of Antiquity <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England</hi> haue been heretofore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioyned by an <hi>Iſtmus</hi> of land, where that ſmall channell runs that now diuides vs. Certaine it is we may ſay with the Poet, <hi>Hic vertex nobis ſemper ſublimis.</hi> One Sunne ſerues our turne by day, and the ſame Pole-ſtarre by night: <hi>At illum ſub pedibus Styx atra videt maneſque profundi,</hi> There be that glory of many ſcattered kingdomes and titles in euery part of the world one: But in this neighbourhood of hearts is yet neerer then that of habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. For kingdomes ſeparate in affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, are like the feet of <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12129:22"/> Image, part yron, part clay, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer mingle well. No two Nations vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heauen (the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Mores</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept) giue more aſſurance of conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie by the affections and diſpoſitions of the people, then theſe two, both of able bodies, and fitting ſpirits, free and ſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, of a ſweetneſſe not allayed with the dulneſſe of ſome, nor blowne vp with the affected grauitie and pride of others, a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and gentle temper, ſuch as ſhould be in men that were created for Cities, and not for Deſarts. Both Nations military and populous, both ioyning together able to afford many armies, without the aid of auxiliary forces. <hi>France</hi> the beſt <hi>Caualry</hi> of the world, and what Infantrie <hi>England</hi> yeelds, <hi>Spaine</hi> can beſt tell.</p>
               <p>Your thrice renowned Father, <hi>Henry</hi> the Great <hi>(Moſt excellent Lady)</hi> knew wel, and loued well this Nation: Nor was the faithfull ſeruice it did him without ſome ſecret and diuine inſtinct that from his loynes ſhould come; <hi>Magnae ſpes altera
<pb facs="tcp:12129:22"/> Britanniae,</hi> a companion fit for the glorie of the Brittiſh Throne, as at this day to our infinite comfort wee all behold. It was the Daughter of <hi>Clotarius,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> that in this Citie liued and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Chriſtian Faith here. From a Daughter of <hi>France</hi> came <hi>Edward</hi> the third of <hi>England,</hi> a glorious and happie Prince. By another match with the Daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> the ſixt of <hi>France</hi> did our <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt reconcile thoſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, which the ſword and warre could neuer doe betweene vs. All ages haue found happineſſe in our vniting: and our diſſenſions neuer reliſhed of others miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune. But if euer, now, euen now was the true period of time to ſummon our ancient affections to a new league, when the Chariot of <hi>Iehu</hi> driues ſo furiouſly, when our neighbours and allies are ſo neare danger, if not ruine, when <hi>(Oh that my tongue could not ſpeake it, but gratiouſly be pleaſed in the day of the gladneſſe of thy heart, O Queene, to be put in minde of it)</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12129:23"/> ſo many Royall branches of that bleſſed tree that now growes in Paradice, liue tranſplanted, nay torne away from their owne proper ſoyle, and ſtill droope by the ouer-dropping of far-ſpreading trees whoſe ſappe is ſower and leafe balefull.</p>
               <p>The Kings of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France</hi> haue euer ballanced the affayres of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, and ſeuerally put weight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the weſterne ſcales, or abated them by counterpoyſe as occaſion of) ſtate hath required. Now they both meete in one ſcale, no doubt the hand of heauen hath written <hi>Mene tekel</hi> vpon the painted wall of their oppoſers, numbred and weighed their ſtrength in the ballance, and found it to light.</p>
               <p>A bleſſing not to haue beene hoped for, but in this happy vnion of your ſacred perſons, in whom (as many waters that make one great riuer) the Royall bloud of many Princes is met to make perfect your greatneſſe in glory &amp; allyance. That of <hi>England Scotland</hi> and <hi>Denmarke</hi> but one
<pb facs="tcp:12129:23"/> diſcent of, in your ſacred perſon (Dread ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne) and though farther (which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps doth beſt, for ſome ſpringes runne cleareſt farre from their head) the bloud of <hi>Spaine</hi> alſo in your moſt excellent perſon (Thrice illuſtrious Queene) the bloud of <hi>France, Nauarre,</hi> and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> in both of you, and not without ſome great and happy prediction (for Heauenly bodies in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction haue their glory doubled) the two Royall branches of <hi>Charlemain,</hi> and <hi>Hugh Capell</hi> are now growne into one tree.</p>
               <p>It was a <hi>Charles</hi> brought the Empire firſt to <hi>France,</hi> A <hi>Charles</hi> that brought it firſt to <hi>Spaine. Non indebita poſcas Regna tuis fatis.</hi> It would ill become our ioyes to take time from yours. Be gratiouſly pleaſed (moſt gratious and excellent Princes) in this poore earneſt, of that humble, Loyall and hearty affections, with which theſe graue Magiſtrates meete the felicity you bring vs, to take
<pb facs="tcp:12129:24"/> poſſeſſion of this City, our hearts, and all that is ours. And the Author of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, powre downe vpon you and vs, the eternity of Ioyes, that the Daughter, Siſter, Spouſe of Kings may be heere made the Mother of Kinges, who when you are crowned with heauenly glory may ſit vpon this Throne for euer. <hi>Et na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti natorum, &amp; qui naſcentur abillis:</hi> to the end of all Kingdomes.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:12129:24"/>
               <p> nothing was wanting that might ſerue ioy or delight.</p>
               <p>On Wedneſday the King and Queene departed from <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and rode in the moſt triumphant manner that might be to <hi>Cobham</hi> Hall, finding (as before I ſaid) all the high-waies ſtrewed with Roſes, &amp; all maner of ſweet flowers, &amp; here at <hi>Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> they lodged al that night, where there was all plentifull entertainment, and nothing wanting that might adde any honour either to the King or Kingdome.</p>
               <p>On Thurſday being the Sixteenth of Iune according to our Computation the King and Queene departed from <hi>Cobham</hi> all the waies prepared as hath been before ſhewed, and ſo in moſt glorious manner came to the City of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> where there was expectation of ſome ſtay; but the day being ſpent too farre they rid thorow the City, notwithſtanding the Maior, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates &amp; Citizens of that City gaue both the King &amp; Queene a noble &amp; moſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty welcome, and the Recorder of the City made vnto them a moſt learned and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12129:25"/> oration, for which both the King and Queene returned back their Royall thanks and ſo paſſing away from the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a braue volley of ſhot and great Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance was deliuered from the Shippes which lay vpon the Riuer.</p>
               <p>From the City of <hi>Rocheſter</hi> the King and Queene came to the Towne of <hi>Graueſend,</hi> where whether it was the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of the <hi>Pourtereeue</hi> or the ouerru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling power of weake (but imagined wiſe) Counſell, or that the preuiledge of old ruſty cuſtome, or ſome other knot which my weake braine is not able to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. I know not, but moſt aſſured it is, that neither the <hi>Portereeue</hi> nor any of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren gaue the King or Queene any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment or tender of ſeruice vntill their highneſſes were come into the very midſt and as it were the very Center of their Towne, and there they made tender of their ſeruice and obedience, which was receiued withall Royall alacrity both of the King and Queene, and ſo they paſſed away in ſtate towards the Bridge
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12129:25"/> where the Barges of State attended their approach, here they diſmounted, and all the Nobilitie attending on each ſide of the Bridge, with a world of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Gentlewomen: here they tooke ſollemne leaue of the King and Queene, and kiſſed both their hands, but ſuch was the excellent diſpoſition of the Queene, and ſo royall and bountifull, her grace and fauour, that to euery La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die that came to kiſſe her hand, ſhee bowed her ſelfe downe and kiſſed their cheekes. Aſſoone as the King and Queene were entred into their Barge of Eſtate, and had a little put off from the ſhoare, the Blocke-houſe which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon the Kentiſh ſhoare firſt let flie all her Ordnance, and ſent foorth a peale, that the Rockes and Chaulkie Cliffes reſounded againe, which was no ſooner finiſhed, but immediately the Blocke-houſe which ſtandeth on the Eſſex ſhore made anſwere with the like Muſicke, and diſcharged all her Ordnance; ſo that the ſmoake mixing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12129:26"/> and meeting together, made a cloud which enterpoſed betwixt the earth and the Sunnes brightneſſe making an Euening at Noone day.</p>
               <p>After the Blocke-houſes had thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged all their Ordnance, then as the King and Queene paſſed along, the Shippes which lay and anchored in the way, diſcharged their vollies diſtinctly after one another; Inſomuch that the vollie was hardly euer found to ceaſe for the paſſage of twelue or fifteene miles together. And the neerer the King and Queene came to the Citie of London, the greater and greater ſtill the volley increaſed. Laſtly, a little before the King and Queene had ſhot the Bridge, the Tower of London let flie her Ordnance, which did ſo thunder and rattle in the aire, that nothing could be heard for the terror of the noice. The throng of ſpectatours was ſo great, that about two hundred being in a ſhippe that lay almoſt drie, and leaning againſt the Wharfe, they with their waight
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12129:26"/> and motion ouerthrew the Shippe into the Thames. And by the way during all this long paſſage, both the King and Queene ſtood publiquely in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Barge, and not onely diſcouered themſelues to euery honeſt and cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full beholder, but alſo with all Royall affabilitie and grace diſtributed their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to all thoſe which came to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire them, ſo that there was not a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſoule which did not in heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude and ſay with the Poet,
<q>
                     <l>Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniunt et in vna ſede mora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur</l>
                     <l>Maieſtas &amp; Amor.—</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And thus at laſt the King and Queene came to the Kings Palace at White-hall, where they were receiued with all the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations of ioy that might bee, and where I am now inforced to leaue them with this true and euer heartie prayer, that it would pleaſe God to bleſſe them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with daies of the longeſt extent that euer made happie any mortall creature, to ſend them faire and flouriſhing Iſſue, and when they ſhall of neceſſitie be tranſlated
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12129:27"/> from this life, that they may raigne with God in glory euerlaſting. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="description">
               <head>¶ The Feaſting of the Duke <hi>de Cheueres,</hi> and the two French Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours, with the declaration of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the King and Queene.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Tueſday being the 21. of Iune, the great Banquetting-houſe of White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall was prepared, and hung very richly with hangings of Silke and Gold, where at the one end of the houſe was placed the Chaires and Cloth of State, at the other end a ſumptuous Cupbord of Plate in manner of an arch; in the middle of the houſe was placed one other Cupbord, not ſo great, but of a farre greater value, being Baſons, Ewers, Cups, Salts, &amp;c. all ſet with Iewels, and of Chriſtall at the root. Then about eleuen of the clock the the King leading his Queen, accompanied with the Duke <hi>de Cheueres,</hi> and his Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, with the two French Embaſſadors, with all the reſt of the Nobilitie and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as well Engliſh, as Scots and French,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12129:27"/> in moſt glorious attires and brauery, and ſuch like as neuer before hath been ſeene in <hi>England,</hi> ſo that the Iewels of the Duke <hi>de Cheueres</hi> were reported to be worth an hundred thouſand pounds. The King being placed on this manner, with the Queene on his right hand, the Articles of the Marriage were read there in publique aſſembly, and approued by the King and the French Embaſſadors: After the which bleſſing being giuen by a Biſhop, the King kiſſed the Queene in preſence of the whole people. After which they reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Priuie Chamber, while the din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was prepared, which was brought vp; after warning giuen with Drummes and Trumpets, whereunto the King, with the Duke and the two Embaſſadors came, the King ſate in his Chaire of Eſtate, the Duke at the end of the Table, with one Embaſſadour at either hand, where in the time of Dinner the King dranke three Healthes to the Embaſſadors, which was proclaimed all ouer the houſe, one to the King of <hi>France,</hi> one to the Queene, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12129:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> one other to the Queene Mother. Thus being feaſted with three great ſeruices, and muſicke playing all the while, they ended the Banquet at foure of the clocke, and retired backe to the Priuie Chamber, where they continued one houre, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the King and the Queene, the Duke, and the reſt of the Nobilitie, Lords and Ladies, returned, where they had dancing for the ſpace of one houre: which being done, the Duke returned to Somerſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe in great State, his Coach hauing eight horſes, Coach-harneſſe, and all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing embrodered, together with three or foure ſcore of Coaches of the richeſt that euer was ſeene in <hi>England,</hi> accompanied with diuers of the Nobilitie.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
